Chapter 41. Moby Dick.
I, Ishmail, was one of that crew. My shouts had gone up with the rest. My
oath had been welded with theirs, and stronger I shouted, and more did I
hammer and clench my oath, because of the dread in my soul. A wild, mystical,
sympathetical feeling was in me. Ahab's quenchless feud seemed mine. With greedy
ears I learned the history of that murderous monster against whom I and all
the others had taken our oaths of violence and revenge. For some time
passed, though at intervals only, the unaccompanied, secluded white whale had
haunted those univilized seas, mostly frequented by the sperm whale fishermen.
But not all of them knew of his existence. Only a few of them
comparatively had knowingly seen him, while the number who, as yet had
actually and knowingly given battle to him, was small indeed. For owing to the
large number of whale cruisers, the disorderly way they were sprinkled over
the entire watery circumference, many of them adventurously pushing their quest
along solitary latitudes so as seldom or never for a whole 12 month or more on a
stretch to encounter a single newselling sail of any sort, the inordinate length
of each separate voyage, the irregularity of the times of sailing
from home, all these with other circumstances, direct and indirect long
obstructed the spread through the whole worldwide whailing fleet of the special
individualizing tidings concerning Moby Tick. It was hardly to be doubted that
several vessels reported to have encountered at such or such a time or on
such or such a meridian a sperm whale of uncommon magnitude and maligny which
whale after doing great mischief to his asalants had completely escaped them. To
some minds it was not an unfair presumption, I say, that the whale in
question must have been no other than Moby Dick. Yet, as of late, the sperm
whale fishery had been marked by various and not unfrequent instances of great
ferocity, cunning, and malice in the monster attack. Therefore, it was that
those who by accident ignorantly gave battle to Moby Dick, such hunters,
perhaps for the most part, were content to ascribe the peculiar terror he bred
more, as it were, to the perils of the sperm whale fishery at large, than to
the individual cause. In that way, mostly the disastrous encounter between
Ahab and the whale had hitherto been popularly regarded.
And as for those who previously hearing of the white whale by chance caught
sight of him, in the beginning of the thing, they had every one of them almost
as boldly and fearlessly lowered for him as for any other whale of that species.
But at length such calamities did ensue in these assaults, not restricted to
sprained wrists and ankles, broken limbs, or devouring amputations, but
fatal to the last degree of fatality.
Those repeated disastrous repulses, all accumulating and piling their terrors
upon Moby Dick, those things had gone far to shake the fortitude of many brave
hunters to whom the story of the white whale had eventually come.
Nor did wild rumors of all sorts fail to exaggerate, and still the more horrify
the true histories of these deadly encounters. For not only do fabulous
rumors naturally grow out of the very body of all surprising terrible events,
as the smitten tree gives birth to its fungi, but in maritime life far more
than in that of terrairma, wild rumors abound, wherever there is any adequate
reality for them to cling to. And as the sea surpasses the land in this matter,
so the whale fishery surpasses every other sort of maritime life in the
wonderfulness and fearfulness of the rumors which sometimes circulate there.
For not only are whalemen as a body unexempt from that ignorance and
superstitiousness hereditary to all sailors, but of all sailors, they are by
all odds the most directly brought into contact with whatever is appallingly
astonishing in the sea. Face to face they not only eye its greatest marvels
but handto jaw give battle to them alone in such remotest waters that though you
sailed a thousand miles and passed a thousand shores you would not come to
any chiseled hearthstone or ought hospitable beneath that part of the sun
in such latitudes and longitudes pursuing to such a calling as he does
the whaleman is wrapped by influences all tending to make his fancy pregnant
with many a mighty birth.
No wonder then that ever gathering volume from the mere transit over the
widest watery spaces, the outblown rumors of the white whale did in the end
incorporate with themselves all manner of morbid hints and half-formed fetal
suggestions of supernatural agencies which eventually invested Moby Dick with
new terrors unbared from anything that visibly appears.
So that in many cases such a panic did he finally strike that few who by those
rumors at least had heard of the white whale, few of those hunters were willing
to encounter the perils of his jaw. But there were still other and more vital
practical influences at work. Not even at the present day has the original
prestige of the sperm whale, as fearfully distinguished from all other
species of the Leviathan, died out in the minds of the whaleman as a body.
There are those this day among them, who, though intelligent and courageous
enough in offering battle to the Greenland or right whale, would perhaps,
either, from professional inexperience or incompetency or timidity, decline a
contest with the sperm whale. At any rate, there are plenty of whalemen,
especially among those whailing nations not sailing under the American flag, who
have never hostily encountered the sperm whale, but whose sole knowledge of the
Leviathan is restricted to the ignoble monster primitively pursued in the
north. Seated on their hatches, these men will hearken with a childish
fireside interest and awe to the wild, strange tales of southern whailing. Nor
is the preeminent tremendousness of the great sperm whale anywhere more
feelingly comprehended than on board of those prows which stem him.
And as if the now tested reality of his might had in former legendary times
thrown its shadow before it, we find some book naturalists, Olison and
Pavvelson, declaring the sperm whale not only to be a consternation to every
other creature in the sea, but also to be so incredibly ferocious as
continually to be a thirst for human blood. nor even down to so late a time
as Kouvier were these or almost similar impressions eaced. For in his natural
history the baron himself affirms that at sight of the sperm whale all fish,
sharks included, are struck with the most lively terrors, and often in the precipit
themselves against the rocks with such violence as to cause instantaneous
death. And however the general experiences in the fishery may amend
such reports as these, yet in their full terribleness, even to the bloodthirsty
item of Pavvelson, the superstitious belief in them is in some vicissitudes
of their vocation revived in the minds of the hunters, so that overroed by the
rumors and portance concerning him, not a few of the fishermen recalled, in
reference to Moby Dick, the earlier days of the sperm whale fishery, when And it
was often times hard to induce long practice right whale men to embark in
the perils of this new and daring warfare. Such men protesting that
although other Leviathans might be hopefully pursued, yet to chase and
point Lance at such an apparition as the sperm whale was not for mortal man. That
to attempt it would be inevitably to be torn into a quick eternity. on this head
there are some remarkable documents that may be consulted.
Nevertheless, some there were who, even in the face of these things, were ready
to give chase to Moby Dick, and a still greater number who, chancing only to
hear of him distantly and vaguely, without these specific details of any
certain calamity, and without superstitious accompiments, were
sufficiently hearty not to flee from the battle if offered.
One of the wild suggestions referred to, as at last coming to be linked with the
white whale in the minds of the superstitiously inclined, was the
unearly conceit that Moby Dick was ubiquitous, that he had actually been
encountered in opposite latitudes at one in the same instant of time. Nor
credulous, as such minds might have been, was this conceit altogether
without some faint show of superstitious probability. For as the secrets of the
currents of the seas have never yet been divulged, even to the most aerodite
research, so the hidden ways of the sperm whale, when beneath the surface,
remain in great part unaccountable to his pursuers, and from time to time have
originated the most curious and contradictory speculations regarding
them, especially concerning the mystic modes whereby, after sounding to a great
depth, he transports himself with such vast swiftness to the most widely
distant points. It is a thing well known to both American and English whale ships
and as well a thing placed upon authoritative record years ago by
Scoresby that some whales have been captured far north in the Pacific in
whose bodies have been found the barbs of harpoons darted in the Greenland
seas. Nor is it to be gained that in some of these instances it has been
declared that the interval of time between the two assaults could not have
exceeded very many days. Hence by inference it has been believed by some
whalemen that the Northwest Passage so long a problem to man was never a
problem to the whale. So that here in the real living experience of living
men, the prodigies related in old times of the inland stallow mountain in
Portugal near whose top there was said to be a lake in which the wrecks of
ships floated up to the surface. And that still more wonderful story of the
Arathusa fountain near Syracuse, whose waters were believed to have come from
the Holy Land by an underground passage.
These fabulous narrations are almost fully equaled by the realities of the whalemen.
Forced into familiarity then with such prodigies as these, and knowing that
after repeated intrepid assaults the white whale had escaped alive, it cannot
be much matter of surprise that some whalemen should go still further in
their superstitions, declaring Moby Dick not only ubiquitous, but immortal. or
immortality is but ubiquity in time.
That though groves of spears should be planted in his flanks, he would still
swim away unharmed. Or if indeed he should ever be made to spout thick
blood, such a sight would be but a ghastly deception. For again in
unsanguined billows hundreds of leagues away, his unsullied jet would once more be seen.
But even stripped of these supernatural surmisings, there was enough in the
earthly make and incontestable character of the monster to strike the imagination
with unwanted power. For it was not so much his uncommon bulk that so much
distinguished him from other sperm whales, but as elsewhere thrown out, a
peculiar snow white wrinkled forehead and a high pyramidical white hump. These
were his prominent features, the tokens whereby, even in the limitless uncharted
seas, he revealed his identity at a long distance to those who knew him. The rest
of his body was so streted and marbled with the same shrouded hue
that in the end he had gained his distinctive appellation of the white
whale. A name indeed literally justified by his vivid aspect when seen gliding at
high noon through a dark blue sea, leaving a milky way wake of creamy foam
all spangled with golden gleamings.
Nor was it his unwanted magnitude, nor his remarkable hue, nor yet his deformed
lower jaw that so much invested the whale with natural terror, as that
unexampled intelligent malignity, which, according to specific accounts, he had
over and over again evinced in his assaults. More than all his treacherous
retreats struck more dismay than perhaps ought else, for when swimming before his
exalting pursuers, with every apparent symptom of alarm, he had several times
been known to turn round suddenly, and bearing down upon them, either stave
their boats to splinters, or drive them back in consternation to their ship.
Already several fatalities had attended his chase. But though similar disasters,
however little bruted ashore, were by no means unusual in the fishery, yet in
most instances such seemed the white whale's infernal of forethought of
ferocity, that every dismembering or death that he caused was not wholly
regarded as having been inflicted by an unintelligent agent.
Judge then to what pitches of inflamed, distracted fury the minds of his more
desperate hunters were impelled, when, amid the chips of chewed boats, and the
sinking limbs of torn comrades, they swam out of the white curds of the
whales direful wrath into the serene, exasperating sunlight that smiled on as
if at a birth or a bridal. His three boats stove around him, and ores and
men, both whirling in the eddies. One captain, seizing the line knife from his
broken prow, had dashed at the whale as an Arkansas duelist at his foe, blindly
seeking with a 6-in blade to reach the fathom deep life of the whale. That
captain was Ahab. And then it was that suddenly sweeping his sickle-shaped
lower jaw beneath him, Moby Dick had reaped away Ahab's leg as a mower a
blade of grass in the field. No turban Turk, no hired Venetian or melee, could
have smote him with more seeming malice.
Small reason was there to doubt then that ever since that almost fatal
encounter Ahab had cherished a wild vindictiveness against the whale. All
the more fell for that in his frantic morbidness he at last came to identify
with him not only all his bodily woes but all his intellectual and spiritual exasperations.
The white whale swam before him as the monomomaniac incarnation of all those
malicious agencies which some deep men feel eating in them till they are left
living on with half a heart and half a lung. That intangible malignity which
has been from the beginning to whose dominion even the modern Christians
ascribe one half of the worlds which the ancient ofightes of the east reverenced
in their statue devil. Ahab did not fall down and worship it like them, but
deliriously transferring its ideas to the abhored white whale, he pitted
himself all mutilated against it, all that most maddens and torments, all that
stirs up the lees of things, all truth with malice in it, all that cracks the
senus and cakes the brain, all the subtle demonisms of life and thought,
all evil to crazy Ahab were visibly personified and made practically
assailable in Moby Dick. He piled upon the white whale's hump, the sum of all
the general rage and hate felt by his whole race from Adam down, and then, as
if his chest had been a mortar, he burst his hot heart's shell upon it.
It is not probable that this monoomania in him took its instant rise at the
precise time of his bodily dismemberment. Then, in darting at the
monster, knife in hand, he had but given loose to a sudden, passionate corporal
animosity, and when he received the stroke that tore him, he probably but
felt the agonizing bodily laceration, but nothing more. Yet when by this
collision forced to turn towards home, and for long months of days and weeks,
Ahab and anguish lay stretched together in one hammock, rounding in mid- winter
that dreary howling Patagonian cape.
Then it was that his torn body and gashed soul bled into one another, and
so interfusing made him mad. that it was only then on the homeward voyage after
the encounter that the final monomomania seized him seems all but certain from
the fact that at intervals during the passage he was a raving lunatic and
though unlimmed of a leg yet such vital strength yet lurked in his Egyptian
chest and was moreover intensified by his delirium that his mates were forced
to lace him fast even there as he sailed raving in his hammock in a straight
jacket He swung to the mad rockings of the gales, and when running into more
sufferable latitudes, the ship, with mild stun souls spread, floated across
the tranquil tropics, and to all appearances the old man's delirium
seemed left behind him with the caphorn swells, and he came forth from his dark
den into the blessed light and air. Even then, when he bore that firm, collected
front, however pale, and issued his calm orders once again, and his mates thanked
God, the dire madness was now gone. Even then Ahab, in his hidden self, raved on.
Human madness is often times a cunning and most feline thing. When you think it
fled, it may have but become transfigured into some still, subtler
form. Ahab's full lunacy subsided not, but deepeningly contracted, like the
unabated Hudson, when that noble Northman flows narrowly, but
unfathomably through the Highland gorge.
But as in his narrow flowing monomomania, not one jot of Ahab's broad
madness had been left behind, so in that broad madness, not one jot of his great
natural intellect had perished. that before living agent now became the
living instrument. If such a furious trope may stand, his special lunacy
stormed his general sanity, and carried it, and turned all its concerted cannon
upon its own mad mark, so that far from having lost his strength, Ahab, to that
one end, did now possess a thousandfold more potency than ever he had sainly
brought to bear upon any one reasonable object.
This is much, yet Ahab's larger, darker, deeper part remains unhinted, but vain
to popularize profoundities, and all truth is profound. winding far down from
within the very heart of this spiked Autel declun where we here stand however
grand and wonderful now quit it and take your way you nobler sadder souls to
those vast Roman halls of themes where far beneath the fantastic towers of
man's upper earth his root of grandeur his whole awful essence sits in bearded
state an antique buried beneath antiquities and throned on tor torsos.
So with a broken throne, the great gods mock that captive king. So like a
chariotid his patient sits, upholding on his frozen brow the piled in tabletures
of ages. Wind you down there, you prouder, sadder souls. Question that
proud, sad king, a family likeness. I, he did beget you, ye young exiled
royalties, and from your grim sire only will the old state secret come.
Now in his heart, Ahab had some glimpse of this, namely, all my means are sane,
my motive, and my object mad. Yet without power to kill or change or shun
the fact, he likewise knew that to mankind he did long dissemble, in some
sort, did still. But that thing of his dissembling was only subject to his
perceptibility, not to his will determine it. Nevertheless, so well did
he succeed in that dissembling, that when, with ivory leg he stepped ashore
at last, no Nantucketer thought him otherwise than but naturally grieved,
and that to the quick, with the terrible casualty which had overtaken him. The
report of his undeniable delirium at sea was likewise popularly ascribed to a
kindred cause, and so too all the added moodiness which always afterwards to the
very day of sailing in the Peekquad on the present voyage sat brooding on his
brow. Nor is it so very unlikely that far from distrusting his fitness for
another whailing voyage on account of such dark symptoms, the calculating
people of that prudent isle were inclined to harbor the conceit that for
those very reasons he was all the better qualified and set on edge for a pursuit
so full of rage and wildness as the bloody hunt of whales. gnawed within and
scorched without by the infixed unrelenting fangs of some incurable
idea. Such a one, could he be found, would seem the very man to dart his iron
and lift his lance against the most appalling of all brutes, or if for any
reason thought to be corporeally incapacitated for that, yet such a one
would seem superlatively competent to cheer and howl on his underlings to the
attack. But be all this as it may, certain it is that with the mad secret
of his unabated rage bolted up and keyed in him, Ahab had purposely sailed upon
the present voyage with the one only and all engrossing object of hunting the
white whale. Had any one of his old acquaintances on shore but half dreamed
of what was lurking in him then, how soon would their agast and righteous
souls have wrenched the ship from such a fish man? They were bent on profitable
cruises, the profit to be counted down in dollars from the mint. He was intent
on an audacious, immittable, and supernatural revenge. Here then was this
gay-headed, ungodly old man, chasing with curses a job's whale round the
world, at the head of a crew, too, chiefly made up of mongrel renegades and
castaways and cannibals, morally infeebled also by the incompetence of
mere unaded virtue or right-mindedness in Starbucks, the invulnerable jolly of
indifference and recklessness in Stub, and the pervading mediocrity in flask.
Such a crew so officer seemed specially picked and packed by some infernal
fatality to help him in his monomomaniac revenge. How it was that they so
aboundingly responded to the old man's eye, by what evil magic their souls were
possessed, that at times his hate seemed almost theirs, the white whale as much
their insufferable foe as his. How all this came to be. what the white whale
was to them, or how to their unconscious understandings also in some dim
unsuspected way he might have seemed the gliding great demon of the seas of life.
All this to explain would be to dive deeper than Ishmael can go, the
subterranean minor that works in us all.
How can one tell Wither leads his shaft by the evershifting muffled sound of his
pick? Who does not feel the irresistible arm drag? What skiff in toe of a 74 can
stand still? For one, I gave myself up to the abandonment of the time and the
place, but while yet all a rush to encounter the whale, could see not in
that brute, but the deadliest ill.